The top of today's דף *Daf* is צדיק חת *Tzadik Chet*, 98.
We are a little behind, we pick up at the top of
צדיק חת *Tzadik Chet* עמוד ב׳ *Amud Bet*, and the current סוגיא
*Sugya* is if somebody borrowed money, although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't
frame it exactly as a loan, sold something or invested in a
business based on a certain amount, a dollar amount was set. And
then when it comes time to pay, the currency that it was
borrowed at or that was agreed upon has now changed and is
no longer valid in this locale. Can he pay back still with
that old currency?
So רב *Rav* says pay back with the new
one and שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says you can still pay back with
the old currency because it's still available somewhere, like you know, there's
still places that are still using it, go to מישן *Meshan* and
use it there. That was the currency you borrowed at, that's the
thing you pay back in and it still is legitimate, it's not
completely נפסל מלכות *nifsal malchus*, you know, it's not completely invalid in
all places. But then רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* limited שמואל
Shmuel, *Shmuel* because that seemed to be a little radical, come on,
it's not fair to the guy giving him back this currency that's
not so usable, and he said that's only if the guy is
headed to that place. If he's headed to מישן *Meshan* then you
can pay him back with that money. Okay, so we pick up
with this. So five lines from the top, איתיביה רבא Rava לרב
נחמן *Aiseiviah Rava leRav Nachman*, so רבא Rava, *Rava* challenged רב נחמן
*Rav Nachman*'s statement like the, you know, contextualizing שמואל *Shmuel* that if
that's the way you're going then that would still be considered legitimate
currency. אין מחללין על מעות שאינם יוצאות *Ein mechalelin al maos she'einam
yotzos*, you cannot transfer the sanctity of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni. *Maaser
Sheni* to money. The תורה Torah *Torah* says that if you're too
far away, you can transfer the sanctity to the money and bring
the money to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, but you cannot do it to
money that is not current, that is not currently in circulation. Thank
you. Excellent. Good money in circulation. כיצד *Keitzad*? How is this? Oh
wow. כיצד *Keitzad*? היו לו מעות כוזביות ירושלמיות *Hayu lo maos Kuzbios
Yerushalmies*,
if you have moneys from כוזביות *Kuzbios*. Now כוזביות *Kuzbios* could mean
like אכזיב *Achziv* from כזיב *Keziv*, which we know is a place,
but רש״י Rashi *Rashi* has an explanation for what כוזביות *Kuzbios* means.
He says it means בן כוזבי *Ben Kuzbi*, it means בר כוכבא
*Bar Kochva*.
Okay, so if you have, and we know they minted money, we
have coins that they minted to you know to the reign of
בר כוכבא *Bar Kochva*, you can actually see this in the museums
in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*. So רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says it
was בר כוכבא *Bar Kochva* currency, ירושלים Yerushalayim בר
כוכבא *Jerusalem Bar Kochva* currency. או של מלכים הראשונים *O shel melachim
harishonim* or anything of earlier kings, right? So that's no longer money
that's in circulation. אין מחללין *Ein mechalelin*, you can't use it. Okay,
that seems pretty straightforward. What's the question? The question is: הא של
אחרונים דומיא דראשונים *Ha shel achronim dumya de-rishonim*, but it sounds like
if you have current, you know, of current kings, even if in
some way it's like past kings. What would be current kings like
past kings? Meaning that these are kings right now and these are
you know governments right now, but as far as you're concerned it's
not relevant. Why? Because there's some other government in some other you
know some other place. So it sounds like the only currency you
can't use is from like past you know kingdoms, right? But currency
that exists now in the world, presumably even if it's not relevant
to you, even if it's not in circulation in your place, the
implication would be that it would be good. הא של אחרונים דומיא
דראשונים *Ha shel achronim dumya de-rishonim*, if it's of the later kings,
current kings, but it's similar to the earlier ones in the sense
that it's not in currency in your location, מחללין *Mechalelin*, it sounds
like it is valid. So that seems to say that currency even
if it's not immediately valid, you know usable here is still valid.
אמר ליה *Amar lei*, הכא במאי עסקינן *Hacha be-mai askinan*, now of
course there could be a big difference by the way between the
parameters of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni *Maaser Sheni* and paying back a
debt. You know, paying back a debt, you know, creates a certain
type of an interpersonal obligation. The parameters of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
*Maaser Sheni* might be enough that somewhere it's considered currency, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes it's the same. So what's his response back?
אמר ליה *Amar lei*, הכא במאי עסקינן *Hacha be-mai askinan*, כשאין מלכויות
מקפידות זו על זו malchuyos makpido zu al zo. *kshe-ein malchuyos makpidos
zo al zo*. It's a case where the given governments, the given
kingdoms, are not מקפיד makpid *makpid*, you know on one another. So
even though you have currency of a different kingdom here, it is
considered to be usable. Now it wasn't exactly clear to me what
אינו מקפידות *einu makpidos* means. Does that mean that here in the
United States people will accept French currency? Is that what it's saying?
I mean that would be an extreme case of אינו מקפידות *einu
makpidos*. Does it mean that it's easy to somehow because there's a
lot of travel between the two places, because there's good relationships, it's
easy to transfer one type of money to another type of money?
You know, it's not exactly clear to me how אינו מקפידות *einu
makpidos* solves the problem. Are we trying to claim that it is
immediately usable here or it's easy enough to get it transferred that
somehow it's still considered to be usable? But one or the other,
that's the answer. That's why it would work. Okay, so then that
would mean that when שמואל *Shmuel* says... when there's a statement that
you can't use the money unless you're heading to that location, it
must be a case where it is מקפיד. makpid, Like because if
it's not מקפיד makpid, we seem to feel like it's good to
use even here. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא כי אמר שמואל
כשמלכויות מקפידות זו על זו. ella ki amar Shmuel k'shemalchuyot makpidot zo
al zo. So one minute. So you're telling me if the governments
are not מקפיד, makpid then the currency is legit, is definitely legit.
Okay. If they are מקפיד, makpid, then you can't use it here
and it's maybe hard to transfer, then it's not legit. But then
how would it work, but if they're מקפיד makpid, and it's not
legit, so if that's true, how would it work if you're even
heading from, you know, the US to France? If it's a case
that they're מקפיד, makpid, let's say it's מקפיד, makpid, let's say it's
Cuba before we lifted the whole embargo. Okay. So if it's a
case of מקפיד, makpid, how you, you know, how you going to
get the money there even if you're heading there? היכי מטי למטה
להו? heichi mati limteih lehu? It assumes that a scenario again, it's
not totally clear to me, but it assumes that a scenario of
אינו מקפיד eino makpid means that the money is even here relatively
usable or easy enough to transfer. And if there's מקפיד, makpid, not
only can you not use it here, but that they will stop
you at the border if you are trying to bring French currency
into France. Okay. I don't exactly get that. Normally they stop you
at the border if you're trying to bring your currency out. But
okay. So if they really are מקפיד, makpid then even if you're
heading to France, how's that make it, thank you, how does that
make it legitimate, right? So how does it make it good currency?
They're going to stop you at the border.
Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says היכי מטי למטה להו? heichi mati limteih lehu? So
the גמרא Gemara says דמטי להו על ידי דחק. demati lehu al
yedei dachak. All right, you can get it to France with a
little difficulty. דלא פכשי, delo pacheshi, they don't search your, they don't
do a border check. They don't ask you to open up your
bags and search your bags. So, you know, if you just keep
quiet and act cool, you'll be able to get it past the
border. ואי משכחי קפדי, ve'im meshkachi kapdei, but if they find that
you have that currency on you, then, you know, they're going to
make you not take it to France, but, you know, so you
have to, I don't know if you'd have to fill out those
customs cards about how much currency you're bringing with you. But whatever
it is, you can get it there. So basically the scenario is
that if here it's relatively usable or transferable, then of course it's
good, and that's the case of מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni What's the
discussion if you can pay back with this currency when it's really
not usable here? It's a case of מקפיד, you have to bring
it to the other place. But you can bring it to the
other place if you just act cool about it. And in that
case,
רב נחמן explains שמואל that if you're heading anyway to France, then
it is considered, you know, good currency and then you can pay
back the loan to the person. I mean if he's heading back
to France, you can pay it back with that type, with that
money, with francs. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תא
שמע. ta shema. So we're still going to try to prove this
one way or the other. אין מחללין על מעות שכאן והן בבבל.
ein mechalelin al ma'ot shekan vehen be'Bavel. So this is obviously the
ברייתא's braita talking from an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael perspective. And it
says you cannot transfer מעשר שני Maaser Sheni to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael, money if you and the fruit are in בבל. Bavel. Now
number one, it's interesting that it deals with מעשר שני maaser sheni
in בבל. Bavel. Normally we assume that these things are only in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael but they did institute the תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u'maasrot in the lands immediately sort of surrounding ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael.
including בבל. Bavel. So you have the fruit in בבל, Bavel, or
actually it doesn't matter where you have the fruit is, the fruit
could be anywhere. But whatever it is, you're in בבל, Bavel, maybe
the fruit's even in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael You're in בבל Bavel
and the money's in בבל. Bavel. And you cannot transfer מעשר שני
maaser sheni to Babylonian currency. I'm sorry, to you're in בבל, Bavel,
the money is in בבל, Bavel, but the money is ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael money. Okay. So you cannot transfer מעשר שני maaser sheni
to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, money if you are in בבל. Bavel.
The point is, and it's a little ironic, because you're going to
be bringing the money to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael. right? But nevertheless,
since it's not usable here, it's not considered money. Now that's the
real challenge to this statement of שמואל, because that's the perfect case.
It's a franc, you're going to France, right? It's shekel, you're going
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. You would think what a better thing
than to be considered money than to transfer to shekel if you're
on your way to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael And it says nevertheless,
since it's not usable here, it's not considered legitimate currency.
אין מחללין על מעות שכאן והן בבבל. ein mechalelin al ma'ot shekan
vehen be'Bavel. You cannot transfer to money here to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael money if
they are in בבל. Bavel. שבבבל והן כאן, shebe'Bavel vehen kan, or
if you're in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you can't transfer to Babylonian
money. Now why in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you can't transfer to
Babylonian money is obvious. You've got to use the money in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael. and it's not usable where you are. It's Babylonian
money. Okay.
שבבבל והן בבבל מחללין. shebe'Bavel vehen be'Bavel mechalelin. And here's the real
irony or whatever. If you're in בבל Bavel and the money is
Babylonian money you can, which is okay, here it's good currency. But
what good is that going to do you? You have to bring
it to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael We'll see in a minute. But
the first, our focus is the first statement. קתני מיהת אין מחללין
על מעות שכאן והן בבבל. katani mihat ein mechalelin al ma'ot shekan
vehen be'Bavel. You can't transfer to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. money that's
in בבל Bavel even though, and the גמרא Gemorah says אעגב דסופיה
למיסק להתם, afgav desofei lemisik lehatam, even though you're going to be
bringing the money there to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael So it seems
very clear that
even if you're headed to that locale, it's not considered currency if
it's not usable in the here and now. So the גמרא Gemorah
says הכא במאי עסקינן כשמלכויות. hacha bemai askinan k'shemalchuyot. זו על זו.
zu al zo.
We're back to that. This is a case where the governments are
מקפיד on one another, so therefore you will not be allowed to
bring your ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. money to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael,
So that's why you can't do it because if you transfer to
שקל shekel here and you try to bring the שקל shekel to
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they're going to stop you at the border.
So the גמרא Gemorah says one minute, אי הכי שבבבל והן בבבל
למאי חזו? eehachi shebavel v'hein b'vavel l'mai chazu? So the גמרא Gemorah
says one minute.
If that's true that, okay fine, I don't exactly get the if
that's true, but the point is, fine, so the only thing you're
allowed to do is transfer to Babylonian money. But oh, here's the
אי הכי. eehachi. You're going to bring the Babylonian money to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael. right? What good is it going to do you
there? It's מלכויות מקפידות זו על זו. zu al zo? They're not
going to let you use Babylonian money in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael
The גמרא Gemara says no, חזו דזבני בהו בהמה ומייתי לירושלים. chazu
d'zavin behu beheima m'isye l'Yerushalayim. So you don't keep it on the
Babylonian money, you transfer your מעשר maaser money to this Babylonian, your
מעשר maaser fruit to this Babylonian money, then use the Babylonian money
to buy some donkeys or horses or whatever and then you bring
those to ירושלים Yerushalayim and then when you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim, then
you transfer it to some other thing and you eat it there.
The funny thing is תוספות Tosafot says you know there's a lot
of sources that say you're not allowed to transfer מעשר שני maaser
sheni... to animals, you can only transfer it to money and so
on, so תוספות Tosafot says well look there's no other option here.
Okay the only way you're going to get the stuff to ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael is if the fruit is too much and the
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael money won't work, בבל Bavel money won't, well
בבל Bavel money will work but it won't be able to then
be used in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael so this really becomes your
only option.
Okay so you switch it to something else once you've made money,
once you've redeemed מעשר שני onto...
then you can switch it to something else, yeah, yeah. So I
mean the other possibility by the way is because I said horses
and donkeys but you could also be a say that you're dealing
with like sheep and cows and then when you get to ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael, you slaughter them and eat them
there, right.
But that seems to be contrary to the intent of מעשר שני
of מעשר שני...
supposed to go to ירושלים Yerushalayim and buy sheep there. Right, right,
although if you were to have brought the actual fruit you would
be bringing the fruit there so now you're bringing cows there but
right, it becomes very bizarre.
Okay, okay, now the גמרא Gemara. says like this, okay והתניא v'ha
tanya one minute, how can you say that it's a case that
you can't use the בבל Bavel money in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael
okay and they're מקפידו makpido זו על זו? If that's true והתניא
v'ha tanya didn't we
teach התקינו שיהו המעות יוצאות בירושלים? hitkinu sheyi'u amos yotzos b'Yerushalayim? They
established that you know because that all money should be accepted in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim right, like you know if you walk in ירושלים Yerushalayim
everywhere you go there's like a little store that's money changer. Have
you ever walked down Jaffa and see money changer stores? But ירושלים
Yerushalayim? everywhere you see them, right, right, because everybody comes to ירושלים
Yerushalayim, you have to be able to deal with all types of
currency. Okay so they established that all currencies should work so if
that's true what's the problem using בבל Bavel money in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael or what's even this scenario of מקפידו? makpido? So אמר
ר' זירא לא קשיא כאן בזמן שיד ישראל תקיפה על אומות העולם
כאן בזמן שיד אומות העולם תקיפה על עצמן. amar R' Zeira lo
kashya kan bizman sheyad Yisrael takifa al umos ha'olam kan bizman sheyad
umos ha'olam takifa al atzman. When we have power then of course
we're going to allow ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. all money to be
used in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael But when we don't have power
when they have power over us then they're going to stop certain
currencies from being used and that can be the reality. Okay so
it's again very interesting you can only logically the best thing to
do is if you're heading to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to transfer
to ארץ ישראל money but in the scenario in which they won't
let you go out of the country with that currency we have
to deal with this thing of transferring it to בבל Bavel money
and then buying something else with it. Alright anyway we're still trying
to prove whether currency that is not good here but good elsewhere
is considered legitimate.
תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught, איזהו מטבע של ירושלים? eizehu
matbe'a shel Yerushalayim? What is the coin of ירושלים? Yerushalayim What does
it look like? דוד ושלמה מצד אחד, David u'Shlomo m'tzad echad, David
and Solomon are on one side of it, וירושלים עיר הקודש מצד
אחר v'Yerushalayim ir hakodesh m'tzad acher and a picture of ירושלים, right,
look just like our currency right now you got a president's face
on the front and like some type of a building on the
back, right? I don't know our classic currency is like that, I
don't know but anyway you have דוד ושלמה David u'Shlomo on the
front right and you have picture of ירושלים on the back.
Okay, and how did they know what the leaders look like because...
oh I guess that's a good point before TV and all those
things that's an... I never thought about that, that makes a lot
of sense why they put that the pictures on the currency.
Okay, ואיזהו מטבע של אברהם אבינו? v'eizehu matbe'a shel Avraham Avinu? What
was the coin used in אברהם אבינו? Avraham Avinu? Oh too bad
Charlie isn't here. Charlie would have told us that they had not
coined money at the time of אברהם אבינו. Avraham Avinu. Okay, זקן
וזקנה מצד אחד... zaken u'zkena m'tzad echad...
I don't know, I don't know, an old man and woman on
one side which would be אברהם Avraham and שרה, Sarah, בחור ובתולה
מצד אחר bachur u'betula m'tzad acher and a young man and woman
on the other, perhaps יצחק ורבקה. Yitzchak u'Rivka. Now by the way
תוספות Tosafot has a great question, look at תוספות, Tosafot, מטבע של...
matbe'a shel... זקן וזקנה מצד אחד zaken u'zekeina mitzad echad בבראשית רבה
be-Bereishis Rabbah דרש זה אגדל שמך שיצא לו מוניטון darash zeh agadel
shimcha she-yatza lo moniton מוניטין monitin בעולם. ba-olam.
I forget what that Greek word is, but obviously stamped off like
your fame will be out in the world, ומהו מוניטין? u-mahu moniton?
זקן וזקנה מכאן בחור ובחורה מכאן. zaken u'zekeina mikan bachur u-v'chura mikan.
Okay,
so that this was the coin, the coin minted in the time
of אברהם Avraham had their image on it. Now תוספות Tosfos has
a little bit of a problem with all of this. Monogram. Anyway,
no, that's not what the word means. Anyway, ונראה ve-nir'eh he says,
ונראה, ve-nir'eh, לא שהיה בו צורת זקן
וזקנה lo she-haya bo tzorat zaken u'zekeina מכאן בחור ובחורה מכאן, mikan
bachur u-v'chura mikan, דאסור לעשות צורת אדם. de-assur la'asos tzorat adam.
You're not allowed to make a human form, which gets into all
interesting questions about what exactly is the איסור issur of making a
human form and is it, what's, does it apply if it's not
fully three-dimensional, if it's not the full form, etc. אלא כך היה
כתוב מצד אחד זקן וזקנה מצד אחד בחור ובתולה. ella kach haya
kasuv mitzad echad zaken u'zekeina mitzad echad bachur u'v'sula. That, I don't
know if that's exactly אברהם's Avraham fame, is that a coin on
one side writes זקן וזקנה. zaken u'zekeina.
Okay. וכן פירש בקונטרס גבי דוד ושלמה ירושלים עיר הקודש כך היו
כתובים במטבע. ve-chein peireish be-kuntress gabei David u-Shlomo Yerushalayim ir ha-kodesh kach
hayu kesuvim ba-matbe'a. Okay, and this is obviously a very fascinating question
about what did, what are the Bar Kochba coins? Do there are
images, don't they?
Yes, of course.
Yeah, but are they human images? I don't think they're human images.
No, they're just pictures of the building. You search it on Google.
The symbols of Jerusalem, I think, are on them.
Yeah, like a לולב? lulav? Right, right, we have a set of
like, yeah. Anyway, so it's not a human image. So it raises
very interesting questions about that. Okay.
The גמרא Gemara says about a certain person that was called, I
forget, חסיד chasid or קדוש kadosh or whatever, because he never looked
at the images on the coins.
Okay, so that whole question about coins and עבודה זרה avoda zara
and images and so on raises interesting questions.
I overpaid a lot.
Maybe he was gonna steal the money.
Wait, but תוספות Tosfos doesn't have a problem with the דוד ושלמה?
David u-Shlomo?
No, then he goes on. וכן פירש בקונטרס גבי דוד ושלמה. ve-chein
peireish be-kuntress gabei David u-Shlomo. Oh, but you are right. Like, why
did he start with that question of אברהם? Avraham? I think it
was because of the מוניטון בעולם moniton ba-olam suggests that it's his
image, it's not just a word.
It requires it's a harder פשט pshat by אברהם Avraham based on
that מדרש Midrash that he quotes.
זקן וזקנה Zaken u'zekeina offers like a freedom that it would be
a word rather than a picture. Aha, if it says זקן וזקנה,
zaken u'zekeina, then you assume that the thing before it was a
picture, right? Because that's the harder case.
Yeah, I don't know. But obviously the same question could be asked
by both if
it says
דוד ושלמה.
David u-Shlomo. Right, right. כתוב. Kasuv. That's what תוספות Tosfos quotes רש"י
Rashi as saying that. Right, okay. Yeah,
yeah, תוספות Tosfos quotes רש"י. Rashi. Yeah, רש"י Rashi says that. Okay.
Moving back to the גמרא. Gemara Okay. בעי מיניה רבא מרב חסדא.
Ba'ei minei Rava me-Rav Chisda. רבא Rava asked רב חסדא. Rav Chisda.
המלווה את חברו על המטבע והוסיפו עליו מהו? Ha-malveh es chaveiro al
ha-matbe'a ve-hosifu alav mahu?
So what we were dealing with was paying back currency that's no
longer current here
but is still being used elsewhere. Now we have another question.
What's הוסיפו? hosifu?
I'm going to tell you. Okay.
You borrowed a thousand שקל shekel from me and the שקל shekel
was a whatever, was a coin a gram size coin of silver.
And now, when it's time to pay back, it's now 1.2 grams
of שקל. shekel. Do you pay back a thousand שקל shekel or
not? Okay, so you're giving me more silver than I gave you.
והוסיפו עליו, ve-hosifu alav, they increased the size of the coin, מהו?
mahu? אמר ליה נותן לו מטבע היוצא באותה שעה. Amar lei nosein
lo matbe'a ha-yotzei be-osah sha'ah. Yeah,
it's still that's still a שקל shekel and guess what, they now
made it bigger, you're still going to pay me back with that,
which really seems funny because it's one thing if it's not based
on, if it's not based on the actual intrinsic value of the
metal. The גמרא Gemara is going to ask this. But if it's
really based on the intrinsic value, even if now they added to
it because there's been inflation, so this now 1.2 gram of coin
could buy what the old 1 gram of coin could buy, nevertheless
it's more silver. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to get to
that. But the first answer is yeah, you pay back based on
the current currency. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה ואפילו
כי נפיא, amar lei ve-afillu ki nafya, even if it's now as
big as a sieve? Like how, really? אמר ליה אין, Amar lei
in, yes. אמר ליה ואפילו כי תרטיא, Amar lei ve-afillu ki tartya,
even if it's as big as like some huge rock? Like how?
אמר ליה אין, Amar lei in, yes, you pay back with the
current currency. So the גמרא Gemara says והא קא זילי פירי, ve-ha
ka zeili peiri, but one minute, the fruit now is a lot
relatively a lot cheaper. If it's a bigger coin, you get more
bang for your buck, you get more fruit from the same coin,
you're giving me back something of greater value. אמר רב אשי חזינן.
Amar Rav Ashi chazinan. Okay wait, we have to assess the situation.
אי מחמת טיבעא זיל מנכינן ליה. Ei machmas tiv'a zil menachinan lei.
If the reason they, you can get fruit cheaper is because there's
now more silver in the coin or whatever the precious metal is,
then you don't pay me back the same number of coins because
then actually the coin has more buying power and therefore you have
to, you don't pay me back with the same coins. ואי מחמת
תרעא זיל, ve-ei machmas tar'a zil, but if actually the reason that
you can get more fruit is because the fruit has now gone
down in price. But the coin really has the same buying power
as before, לא מנכין ליה, lo mankin lei, then you don't. So
even though it's a bigger coin, if it has the same buying
power as before you pay me back with it. So now finally
the גמרא Gemara turns to asking the question about the fact, but
there's more precious metal in the coin. The גמרא Gemara says והא
קשבח לענין נסקא, veha kashvach le'inyan naska,
but נסקא naska is like the raw metal, okay, it's like a
metal bar. Okay wonderful, you're telling me that this שקל shekel has
the same buying power as the old שקל, shekel, but there's more
silver in it. So isn't that still giving me back more than
I gave, which is a great question, right, about
the
abstract value of money when there's also, you know, intrinsic value to
it. So on one hand you're giving me... I gave you a
thousand שקל, shekel, you're giving me back a thousand שקל, shekel, it's
actually the same buying power. On the other hand, it's more silver.
So what's the story?
Abstract, and money, and it's
good because you could melt it down. Right. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא, Ella, fine, you know what maybe you're right. כי הא
דרב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, ki had d'Rav Papa ve'Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, עבד עובדא בזוזי דאגרדמיס טייעא, avad uvda b'zuzei
d'agardamis taya,
they dealt a case with this money that was lent out and
they went to this אגרדמיס, agardamis, which at least Soncino translates as
some type of a... of... not a businessman, but some type of
an overseer of like monetary issues. How do they translate it there?
What אגרדמיס, agardamis, it's not a name apparently, it's a title.
אגרדמיס Agardimus the Arab.
Oh, they translated it as a name. I don't know, Soncino translated
it as a title, like it was some type of a... of
like a, you know, somebody in charge of currency. Anyway, but okay,
a trader or something. Anyway, this Arab trader or this Arab who
is knowledgeable in these issues, and he basically said עד יהב תמניא.
ad yahav tamnya. You're right that basically the coins had changed and
now eight new coins are worth ten old coins. So it seems
like the גמרא Gemara is reversing itself. It seems like the גמרא
Gemara is saying that if the coins actually do contain more precious
metal, then you don't pay back based on the face value of
them, even if they're all still called שקל, shekel, you pay back
based on how much of the old coins... the weight, how much
of the new coins, you know, what is the equivalent of the
new coins in the old currency. Okay?
But so we don't really care about market prices and all that
at all, I mean...
Right. Well, that's always true. If I lend you a thousand and
you pay me a thousand, we don't look at, oh, you know,
it's not a thousand dollars in 2010 dollars, it's a thousand dollars
when you pay me back. Okay, so but then the חידוש chidush
here is that even if they adjusted the currency so that maybe
it would have the same buying power, you still look at the
precious metal value of the currency.
But actually, let's say I really did say that. You pay back
in 2010 dollars, but I didn't specify which way it can go.
So do I suffer a loss or get the gain?
Yeah, I don't know. That raises interesting ריבית ribbit questions. Yeah, that
raises interesting ריבית ribbit questions. If you could say I want you
to pay me back in val... you know, based on the consumer
price index or whatever. It's an interesting question, yeah, how you could
arrange that. All right, let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says
now we switch gears back to בבא קמא Bava Kamma topics, and
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, I mean this, you know, but this is
somewhat בבא מציעא Bava Metzia topics about coins and currency and whatever.
Anyway, but back not only to the end of בבא קמא Bava
Kamma but more to like an earlier part of בבא קמא Bava
Kamma to מזיק mazik issues. And this will be fun, and this
might remind you of some stuff we had earlier.
Let's take a look.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הזורק מטבע של חבירו לימא הגדול, hazoreik matbeia
shel chaveiro l'yama hagadol, I go and I take Michael's silver dollar
and I throw it into the ימא הגדול. yama hagadol. Doesn't matter
silver dollar, just... anyway, I throw it into the Mediterranean. Okay. פטור,
patur, I don't have to pay you anything. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
אמר המנח קמך, amar hamunach kamach, what, the money's right there? Just...
go just dive down, it's right there in the ocean. Okay. אי
בעי לישקלה, im ba'i lishkla,
if you want, go take it. Now, והני מילי בצלולין, vehani mili
b'tzululin, that's only if the water is clear, דקחזי ליה, d'kachazei lei,
you can still see it. אבל עכורין דלא חזי ליה, לא, aval
achurin d'lo chazei lei, lo, but if it's dirty, if it's cloudy
water and you can't see it, no. והני מילי דאדיאדויי, vehani mili
d'adiyaduye, now that's only if I basically knocked it out of Michael's
hand and it flew out of his hand, because then I'm a
מזיק, mazik, I'm not a גזלן. gazlan. So the question is, did
I damage the money? Right? Did I destroy the money? Is it
destroyed? And if it's there on the bottom of the Mediterranean, it's
not destroyed. But we'll get back to that in a minute. אבל
שקליה בידיה, aval shaklei biyadei, if I grabbed it out of Michael's
hand and then I threw it into the Mediterranean, מיגו דגזליה, migu
degazlei, then I stole it. It doesn't matter whether it's there or
not there. My act of grabbing obligated me to reimburse you. So
either I have to dive down to the bottom of the Mediterranean
and get it or I have to give you other money. What
happens afterwards is not your issue, the act of גזילה gezeilah obligates
me. השבה בעי מעבד, hashavah ba'i me'vad, I have to do restoration.
So the question is fine, but as a מזיק, mazik, if I
don't take it, I knock it out of Michael's hand, it's not
considered damage. Now really, it's not damage that's at the bottom of
the Mediterranean just because you can see it? So תוספות Tosafot says
it's not really about being able to see it, it's being about
able to retrieve it. Like if it's retrievable, you could hire... somebody
to go dive down and get it, even though the cost of
hiring that person would be more than the value of the coin.
Because it's retrievable, it's not considered to be destroyed. Okay? Now תוספות
Tosafot *Tosfos* says actually that would be true even if it wasn't
visible, even if it was cloudy water, if in theory it was
retrievable. Now I'm not so sure. I think that you might need
both, right? You might need the fact that both it's visible, so
if it's visible it's still considered there. Look, you see it, it's
still there. It's not like I've destroyed it; it's just hard to
get to. And it has to be possible to get to. It
would seem to me that if it's not visible and difficult to
get to... I mean, if it's not visible and easy to get
to, if I covered it up with a piece of paper, I
didn't destroy it, okay? But if it's the combination of not visible
and hard to get to, even if it's possible, to me it
would seem that that's enough to define it as if it's destroyed.
Okay, but תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says it's irrelevant really if it's visible
or not visible. The only issue is, is it in theory retrievable
or not? Okay? But it's still a very strange idea, right? Like
imagine I knock something out of your hands and it... you know,
it's an interesting question. I knock something out of your hands, it
rolls down, it rolls into the gutter, you know, they have the
drains in the middle of the street, and now it's at the
bottom of the gutter. So we all know like in theory you
can go ahead and get it, right? Can you say 'I'm not
getting it, pay me for it'? Or can I say to you,
'What do you mean pay you for it? Go get it!' Or
can you say, 'Okay, well you've got to be the one to
get it, right?' So this gets back to the issue about גרמא
grama. בנזיקין *grama b'nezikin*. If we can concede that the object is
not yet destroyed, even though now because of what I've done it's
going to cost you time and money and effort to retrieve it,
that's just indirect cause of loss. As long as I haven't destroyed
the object, I still remain exempt. Very, very strange, okay? So let's
keep on seeing, as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to pile
up these cases about all these bizarre cases of where you're going
to be exempt, at least according to רבה Rabba *Rabbah*, and then
there's going to be a little bit of a pushback. Yes?
In the first case, was it intentional?
Could have been. Did he throw it or did he drop it?
Well, if he picked it up and threw it, then it would
be גזילה *gezeilah*. But he could have intentionally knocked it so it
would fall, right. Yeah, and even if you're intentional, you know, גרמא
grama בנזיקין *grama b'nezikin*, which is crazy. So eventually there's going to
be some pushback. Let's keep on going, okay? מתיב רבא Masiv Rava,
*Maysiv Rava*. So רבא Rava *Rava* challenges. אין מחללין על מעות שאינם
ברשותו *Ein mechallalin al maos she'einam birshuso*. We're back to this מעשר
שני *maaser sheni*. You can't transfer מעשר שני *maaser sheni* money to
money that you don't have in your, under your control. כיצד *Keitzad*?
היו לו מעות בקסטרא *Hayu lo maos beKastara*, let's say you have
money in this far-away place called קסטרא *Kastara*, או בהר המלך *o
beHar Hamelech*, yeah, I don't know where these places are, או שנפל
כיסו לימא הגדול *O shenafal kiso l'yama hagadol*, or your wallet's on
the bottom of the sea, okay? אין מחללין *Ein mechallalin*. You can't
say, 'Oh, I'm transferring my מעשר שני *maaser sheni* to my wallet
that's on the bottom of the Mediterranean.'
So you see that it's considered to, to not exist. Now, there's
a very funny question because it's not really that it doesn't exist,
it's in קסטרא *Kastara* and you still can't do it. Does that
mean that if I, if I somehow without technically stealing it took
your money and moved it to קסטרא *Kastara*, I would be considered
to have destroyed it? I mean, maybe.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here thinks that it's like
it doesn't exist. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, it's destroyed.
אמר רבה Rabba *Amar Rabbah* no, that's not that it's destroyed. שאני
עניין מעשר דבעינן מצוי בידך *Shani inyan maaser d'beinan matzui b'yadcha*. When
it comes to מעשר *maaser*, it's not enough that the money is
considered around, it has to be considered accessible, okay? Found, accessible. How
do you know that by מעשר *maaser*? רחמנא *Rachmana* אמר *amar* וצרת
הכסף בידך *v'tzarta hakesef b'yadcha*. Bind the money to your hand, which
means the money you use has to be as if it's directly
in your hand, has to be accessible. Okay, but it's still around,
so you're not חייב chayav *chayav* as a מזיק mazik *mazik* just
because you did that. Okay, that's number one. Is it considered to
be destroyed and damaged if it's at the bottom of the sea?
Now we're going to get to another case.
Okay, why isn't that an example of it's not...
It's a special מעשר שני *maaser sheni* requirement that doesn't exist elsewhere.
By מעשר שני *maaser sheni*, it's not enough that you own the
money and that it's around, you have to... it has to be
accessible.
Ah, so accessibility is a middle category between having it and it
being destroyed that's now being limited, it's in מעשר שני *maaser sheni*.
מעשר שני *maaser sheni* exactly.
Which is strange, because accessibility should be like the general principle.
Yeah, but he is right, the תורה Torah *Torah* emphasizes your access
to the מעשר שני *maaser sheni* money.
Yeah,
but it's not just, it's not just for money by מעשר שני
*maaser sheni*. It would be also by something else, let's say you
put it into bullion, you would also have that requirement by bullion,
right? It's not just coin.
Well, but you can only redeem it on coins. You can only
redeem מעשר שני *maaser sheni* on coins.
Okay, so right now we're saying let's say I borrow money from
you and then the time to repay... so yeah, yeah I have
money, you know...
No, that's a separate question. That's separate, whether you can repay. That's
what we discussed earlier. You might have an obligation to restore me
to the way I was because you borrowed that money. You know,
what's considered legitimate paying back is a different question. But here it's
a question of מזיק mazik.
*mazik*. No, no, I'm asking...
No, that's presumably that's not good, you have to actually give it
to me. Okay, ואמר רבה *v'amar Rabbah*, but I'm not going to
go into that. אמר רבה *Amar Rabbah* השף מטבע *hashaf matbeia*. Now
we're going to take it further. Okay, that was something that it's
around just not accessible. Now listen to this case. You go ahead
and you flatten somebody's coin. You take his coin and you basically
smooth the, you know, image, you flatten it, you rub it off,
so it's no longer... I mean, it still has precious metal, you
haven't taken any silver, you just flattened it. So you can't use
it now as a coin. Now it still has precious... Precious metal,
but clearly its fact of having been minted as a coin increased
its value from its pure precious metal value. Okay, so שף מטבע
של חברו פטור, Patur, you're exempt. מאי טעמא? דלא עבד ולא מידי.
Mai ta'ama d'lo avad velo midi? I didn't do anything, it's still
all there, I just rearranged the parts, right? So I went and
I took
your bronze Picasso statue, and I just, like, smashed it, but it's
all there, I just rearranged the parts, so I didn't do anything.
Now, what you could say is that this is particularly about coins.
The גמרא Gemara is not going to limit it to coins, but
it actually would have made a lot of sense to limit it
to coins, because we just saw that ninety, I don't know what
it is, I'm making up this number, but ninety-five percent of the
value of coins is actually the precious metal at that time. The
reason for minting it was really just as a way that everybody
should immediately know that it genuinely had that amount of precious metal
in it, right? So there you could say the value added by
the fact that it was minted is more of an abstract value,
and its real value is still fundamentally all there. So this is
an idea that could have made more sense by coins, but the
גמרא Gemara is not going to limit it to it. The גמרא
Gemara... is going to basically say that according to רבא, Rava you
are not a מזיק mazik if you don't take away any of
the physical object, even if you rearrange the object. Okay, so again,
I feel like if you break a table into parts, you've taken
it away by, you know, by removing one part from the next.
But if you basically take some piece of metal and you completely
rearrange it, if I poke holes in it, it's still there. If
I take your car and I bang it up, right, the whole
car is still there, it's just got dents in it, I didn't
take any piece of metal away, I'm not a מזיק. mazik Okay,
it's totally crazy. Okay, what?
So
מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama? דלא עבד ולא מידי? D'lo avad velo midi.
והני מילי דמחי בקורנסא, V'hani mili d'machyei bekurnasa,
that's only if you hit it with a hammer, דטרשיה, detarshei, like
smooth, and you flattened it. אבל שפי בשופני, Aval shapei beshufinei, if
you sort of if you rubbed it with a like with a
like type of a plane or something, you know, something that actually
would remove some of the metal, like a file, חסורי חסריה, Chisorei
chasrei,
then that's an act of מזיק mazik, and then you have to
pay for it.
So what's the definition of breaking something?
According to this, it's actually, you know, somehow removal of some of
the material. You know,
you've taken, you know, you've removed its... it's crazy. I don't know
why that's the definition.
Like if I take a baseball bat and I cut it in
half,
that's a מזיק mazik, because, no, because you removed one piece from
the other. You don't actually remove the material from the world, okay?
You know, you just you detach the material.
Okay, but you got your Picasso, it's identical and you've melted it
down. Right. Well, how's that different than cutting the bat in half?
Well, if by the process of melting it down, the pieces have
separated. But if you bang it and you flatten it, if I
take, if I go, if it's all one piece, I go to
your Michelangelo painting and I paint over it. I didn't take any
piece away, I just added. You should be paying me, I added
all this nice red paint! Maybe Picasso... anyway. What? It would have
been a Warhol, it
wouldn't have been a...
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, thank you, that was ignorant of me. Okay,
I meant Rembrandt, obviously, obviously. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay,
מתיב רבא, Rava so רבא Rava challenges, and he, again, you could
have said he was just talking about coins, but from רבא's Rava.
question and the גמרא's Gemara answer, it understands that it abstracts this.
הכהו על עינו וסמאה, Heika'u al eino vesima'ah, if you hit a
slave on his eye and you blinded him, על אזנו וחרשה, Al
ozno vechershah, his ear and you made him
deaf, עבד יוצא לחירות, Eved yetzei lecheirus, the slave would go free.
כנגד עינו ואינו רואה, Keneged eino ve'eino ro'eh, if it was like
you hit the wall and was right next to his eye and
somehow the shock blinded him, or כנגד אזנו ואינו שומע, Keneged ozno
ve'eino shomei'a, near his ear and he couldn't hear, אין עבד יוצא
לחירות, Ein eved yetzei lecheirus, he doesn't go free. Anyway, the point
is, is that look, you hit his ear, you don't you didn't
take any part of his body away, and you're considered... now of
course you could say who knows, maybe that's a separate הלכה halacha
than מזיק, mazik. maybe a slave going free has its own parameters.
But anyway, but he says, presumably, this idea you have to take
something away to define it as an act of מזיק, mazik and
that would apply even to this case of of injuring a slave.
So why does he go free? So the גמרא Gemara. says, no.
רבא לטעמיה, Rava leta'amei, רבא Rava goes according to his reasoning. דאמר
רבא חרשו לאביו, De'amar Rava chersho le'aviv, if somebody made his father
deaf by hitting him in the ear, נהרג, neherag, he's killed. Now
the idea that if somebody smites and wounds his father, it's it's
חייב מיתה chayav misah is only if it's a wound that makes
blood, draws blood. So how by hitting him in the ear did
you draw blood? אי אפשר לחרישה בלא חבורה, Ee efshar lecharisha belo
chavurah, you can't make somebody deaf without causing some interior wound. דטיפת
דמא נפלה ליה באזניה, Detipas dama naflah leih be'ozneih, it must be
a drop of blood fell in the ear, there must have been
some interior wound. Okay, so therefore, once that's true, we're saying, oh,
so making somebody deaf caused some interior wound, so that was the
case of חסורי חסריה, Chisorei chasrei, you took something away, right? So
that's why it's considered an act of מזיק. mazik. Okay, but if
you actually managed, again, I don't get it, if I went ahead
and I broke somebody's finger, right, and I broke the bone, well,
that's I guess I took something away, I separated one part of
the bone from the other. But anyway, now we see the גמרא's
Gemara not limiting this to... to coins, whether it's מזיק mazik, or
חובל, chovel, you're only considered to have done an act of damage,
not only if it's a direct act to the thing or the
person, but if it actually takes something away, which is a very
strange idea.
Well, it takes one part of a bone away from the other
part of the bone. What?
No, but they
separate.
No, but anytime you do something, you separate two parts, and you
haven't made it disappear from the world.
If I took the bumper off of your car and leave it
right
next to it, that would be a מזיק. mazik. But if I
bang it up, that would not be מזיק, mazik, right? Don't remove
any paint. If in the act of banging, some paint scraped off,
then you'd be considered a מזיק. mazik Because you're only removing it.
But if I painted over your painting... Exactly.
I know. These ideas are like, this is like, what? Like, how
could we say...
if you said this on the street, you'd be alive for about
four minutes.
I have to tell you, I mean look, in a minute we're
going to talk about גרמי, Garmi, you know, as a way of
sort of covering this gap here. But I have to tell you,
because it's this week's פרשה, Parsha, I think I mentioned this yesterday
that, or on שבת, Shabbos, that the ר"ן, Ran, the famous דרשה
Drasha of the ר"ן Ran on this week's פרשה Parsha of שופטים,
Shoftim, he basically says that why does the תורה say to make
a king? Because he says if you tried to, if you tried
to use the תורה law in real society, it won't work. Okay?
So he says that these laws are all for some sort of
abstract platonic type of reality, but they don't really work in real
society. Well, I exaggerated. Anyway, so he says you need the king,
and the king is going to come and he's going to make
the laws that are actually going to fill all the gaps and
are going to make this functional and they're going to make you
able to live in a society based, you know, based on these
laws. Which raises interesting questions: what's the point of it if they're
not really able to succeed in the real world? But anyway, this
would be a perfect example of that. Let's keep on going.
The גמרא... Gemara you might be suggesting what the גמרא Gemara is
doing is being very exacting to the point of absurdity in order
to justify the need for a more nuanced category.
That's an interesting backwards way of thinking. We're going to show how,
how far these laws fall short in order to justify why we
need something else. It hasn't even said though we need something else.
Let's keep on going. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר
רבא: Ve'amar Rava: הצורם אוזן פרתו של חבירו, Hatzorem ozen parato shel
chaveiro, if you basically make, pierce the ear of your friend's cow,
פטור, Patur, you're exempt. Even though... What is that? In my ears
as an upright... well that's interesting. Okay, that was a podcast. You
can all figure out which podcast that is. Okay, anyway. I've got
to stop my iPhone
from talking up on me. Anyway. Okay. So, this made the animal
have a wound and it is not fit to be brought as
a קרבן. Korban. Okay? So you're פטור, patur. you're exempt. מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, what reason? פרה כדקיימא קיימא, Para kidekaima kaima, the cow
looks as good as before. Now, it doesn't mean that there was
not some normal חבלה Chabala because presumably poking a hole in the
ear, you know, did cause something to come out, okay, but it
seems like the emphasis is the second part: דלא עבד ולא מידי,
Dlo avad velo midei,
you didn't really do anything that would change its value. Okay, a
cow with a hole in the ear without a hole in the
ear is the same value. וכולי שוורים לאו לגבי מזבח קיימי. Vekulei
shovarim lav legabei mizbe'ach kaimi. And not all oxen are used to
be brought as sacrifices. The fact that you can't bring it as
a sacrifice doesn't really change its value. Now the question is: what
is he really saying? It sounds like his point is the second
part. It's not like he's just saying 'oh a hole in something'.
I mean, it is true, sometimes you can make a hole in
something without taking anything away because you're just like pushing the stuff
to the side. I don't know if that works like when you
make, when you pierce a hole in the ear. Does some flesh
come out? No. Yes, no. Little מחלוקת Machlokes here.
Oh you do get blood.
Oh you do get blood. Okay fine. Okay, but some blood comes
out, something comes out. Okay, so it doesn't seem like it was
the previous case about you weren't מחסיר Machsir anything. It seems like
it was a case of that it's you know, you didn't change
the market value. But then what's he telling me? He's not telling
me that it wasn't an act of מזיק, mazik. he's telling me
that you pay for the loss of value but the loss of
value is zero because the market value doesn't change. I don't need
him to tell me that. And maybe the market value does change!
Even if most people don't bring the oxen as a קרבן, Korban,
maybe there's a ten dollar premium on unblemished oxen for people who
do want to bring it as a קרבן. Korban. So it's not
exactly clear what his חידוש Chidush is. It might be that his
חידוש Chidush is, is that how do you define you know what's
considered damage? Like, like you know going back to the car example,
like what happens when like you know you're trying to back in
or back out of a parking space and you make like a
tiny little mark on this guy's car. So in theory he could
say you gotta pay me whatever, 50 bucks, I got to take
it to the mechanic, he's got to paint it or whatever. But
in a certain type of a reality, like even if things are
changed a little bit, do we really look at that as that
the object has been damaged, right? If I made a little scratch
on something that really nobody cares about or pays attention to, even
you know would that be considered an act of having damaged it.
It might cost money to fix it but at what case when
we don't look at that as though it's a different type of
a thing, as that it's been injured, you know, been damaged, is
it even defined. So it seems to me that's more what he's
saying, not that... Look, the market, it is a מעשה מזיק, maise
mazik, but the market, but the cost is zero. It seems more
in this type in an agricultural society, you don't look at a
cow with a hole in the ear different than a cow without
a hole in the ear even though in theory it might change
for somebody interested in it as a קורבן korban it might be
worth a different amount. Jenna, yes.
I'll give you even better as an example, like someone who wants
to take the auto to get the scratch, and you look around
the rest of the car and it's scratched.
All right, exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. Right. So it might, is it an act of מזיק
mazik. if in this society nobody pays attention to that? Right.
Exactly. So you have your nice פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Right. All
right.
So פרה אדומה parah adumah would be different. Right.
All right. But put an עול ol on it. It looks the
same, in fact, it might even want to eat it but now
it's פסולה. pesulah.
Brilliant. So that's the next case in the גמרא. Gemara Let's take
a look. Yeah. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this, which is
funny why the גמרא Gemara brings this because רבא specifically talked about
normal cows that aren't being to be brought as a sacrifice. Let's
take a look. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רבה.
mative Rabba. So רבא is making all these statements and רבה keeps
on pushing back. So רבה challenged. העושה מלאכה במי חטאת, Ha'oseh melacha
bemei chatat, if you do work with water that was going to
be used for the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Now תוספות Tosafot says,
of course this is different, if you're dealing in פרה אדומה parah
adumah world, all of this is למזבח קאי, lemishbei'ach kai, is going
to be used for הקדש hekdesh purposes. So obviously it would be
different. So תוספות Tosafot says, so it's bizarre that he's even bringing
these examples. So תוספות Tosafot says that's why we're talking about מי
חטאת. mei chatat. The water is water before the ashes have been
added. So water that you're intending to use for פרה אדומה, parah
adumah, it still doesn't have any status as such. So therefore he
thinks it's like relevant that we shouldn't consider this to be a
damage according to your logic. ובפרת חטאת, Uvifarat chatat, or if you
do מלאכה melacha with your the cow that's going to be a
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei
adam vechayav bidinei shamayim. It's היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, you
can't see that it's been damaged, but obviously now the thing can't
be used for that purpose. So you're exempt in worldly court, but
you're חייב chayav. up in heaven.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מלאכה הוא דלא מינכר היזיקה. melacha hu
d'lo mincar hezeka. The reason you're exempt is because you only did
מלאכה melacha and it's not visible. אבל צורם, Aval tzorem, but if
you were to make a hole in the ear, דמינכר היזיקה, demincair
hezeka, that it would be visible, הכי נמי דמיחייב בדיני אדם, hachi
nami demichayav bidinei adam, you would be חייב. chayav. Now the obvious
answer is: yes, because it's a פרה חטאת, parah chatat, it's not
a normal cow, of course that is. But then the answer is
a strange answer that the גמרא Gemara doesn't draw that line and
תוספות deals grapples with that. אמרי, Amri, the גמרא Gemara says, הוא
הדין דאפילו צורם פטור. hu hadin d'afilu tzorem patur. Even if you
made a hole you'd be exempt. והא קמשמע לן, Veha kamashma lan,
דאפילו מלאכה דלא מינכר היזיקה, d'afilu melacha d'lo mincar hezeka, even מלאכה
melacha where it's not visible, חייב בדיני שמים. chayav bidinei shamayim. You're
still חייב בדיני שמים. chayav bidinei shamayim. Again, very, very strange because
you would think if you made a hole in the ear of
a פרה אדומה parah adumah you'd have to pay. That would clearly
be מזיק. mazik So תוספות tries to emphasize that the discussion is
more about the water where it's less obviously going to be used
for that purpose. Okay, another crazy statement of רבא. ואמר רבא, Veamar
Rava, השורף שטרותיו של חבירו, hashoref shetarotav shel chavero, actually this one
is not as crazy as the other.
Okay, השורף שטרותיו של חבירו hashoref shetarotav shel chavero פטור. patur? If
you burn your
friend's documents, IOUs, loan documents, and now he can't collect the loan,
you don't have to pay him anything. Even though he's now out
all that money because he's not going to be able to collect.
ואמר ליה, Veamar lei, yeah, you have to pay him the value
of paper. ניירא קליתי מינך, Nayara kaliti minach, I only just burnt
paper. You want me to pay you for paper, I'll pay you
for paper. The fact that you can't collect the loan, that the
thousand-dollar document wasn't an object worth a thousand dollars. The guy still
owes you the money. The fact that I made it hard for
you to collect, that's not an intrinsic that's not I didn't destroy
the loan. Okay, so מתיב ליה רמי בר חמא. Mativ lei Rami
bar Chama. By the way, apparently a lot of pogroms in the
Middle Ages happened as excuses for them to go in and to
burn all the loan documents. Okay, מתיב ליה רמי בר חמא, Mativ
lei Rami bar Chama, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי
דאיכא סהדי דידעי מאי הוה בשטרא, Ei d'ika sahadei d'yad'ei mai hava
beshitra,
if there are witnesses that know that the document said there,
that David owed Michael a thousand dollars and I burnt the document,
so they're telling me I should be paying a thousand dollars because
now he can't collect. So why can't he collect? They know that
they saw what's in the document. So ליכתבו ליה שטרא מעליא, lichtevu
lei shitra ma'alya, let the witnesses write a new שטרא, shitra, they
saw what the document said. Okay, let them reproduce a replacement.
And then for what was your חידוש chiddush by saying that you're
פטור?
patur. Yeah, what's your חידוש? chiddush? Everybody would just get a replacement
document. אי דליכא סהדי, Ei d'leika sahedi, if no witnesses saw what
was written in it, אנא מנא ידעינן, ana mena yad'inan, so then
even if I were liable to you, how much do we know
was written in it that I should be have to pay? That's
a good question. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רבא said, תהא במאמינו.
Tehei bema'amino. No, it could still be a case where basically I
burnt Michael's documents and I say, Michael, I will trust you what
was in those documents and I will pay you whatever the court
says I have to pay for having destroyed them. And so even
though I'm prepared to believe Michael what was written in the
documents and he says it said that David owed me a thousand
dollars, I still don't have to pay because I only
destroyed... we haven't even said בדיני שמים. bidinei shamayim. Okay, because that's
just seen as... It doesn't have any intrinsic value. Now, I do
have to say what I don't understand about this is like I
guess it's the whole question about what intrinsic value means. But like
why it isn't seen as a type of a כלי? kli? Like
why don't you look at this document as a type of an
instrument that allows for the collection of a loan? Like is something
only intrinsic if it works in terms of like its physical properties?
Like if I have like, I don't know, you know, I have
some type of a pass that lets me get in free to
movies, okay, and you go ahead and you burn destroy. We'll say,
well, it had no intrinsic value, I mean, you know, it wasn't
like you could use physically the piece of paper to do something,
right? I mean, why isn't that not just like an object that
actually serves a function, right? Is it because it's a function based
on the conventions of society and not a function based on the
physical world that makes it not having intrinsic value? You know, I
don't exactly get why
it's not even it's not even that it's functional in other realms
as well because if it's it had you can't like turns its
its functionality in the in the temple, like in the cult, doesn't
matter at all either. Right? It's not just even functional material.
It's just right, that's what I'm saying, it has to be like
it somehow has some it physically can be used, right?
I don't know if it even can be used. Why does it
even have
I
don't understand why does a piece of art have intrinsic value? The
value of a piece of art has is aesthetic. Why is that
not why is that
not a piece of art work is the exact same thing as
the voucher to get into the concert. Right. They're just, right, that
like the culture.
That like paper and the paint does not
right, well, right, but presumably if I destroy a piece of art
I have to pay for its market value. Is the difference maybe
the difference is that it doesn't have a market value, that I
can't sell this IOU on the open market.
Yes, it's just like a really case of that's it's trait and
it's it has to do with customs and a piece of art
that comes in and it's sort of
like
an abstract piece of art
and
the question is whether or not this has any intrinsic value because
it's like it's called the bird, the the sculpture, but it's just
like that. Right. So is that and it's actually should be okay
okay got it got it yeah idea that it's like only valuable
to you it's probably really like if that movie pass has your
name right right right it's non-transferable, right. So that could be. But
still, I don't know, and if I have a an airplane ticket,
right, and you destroy my airplane ticket and I can it's a
non-transferable ticket and that would have let me get on the flight,
maybe that would be the same. It only it doesn't really destroy
it only destroys the proof that I bought the you know that
I bought the right. It's a strange idea, I gotta tell you.
Anyway, let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
The definition of intrinsic value's also got to be assumed why something
is That's what I'm saying.
I don't exactly know, I don't exactly know what defines intrinsic value,
you know. I mean, yeah.
We've decided as a society that gold has got intrinsic Right, exactly,
right, exactly.
Why do precious metals have intrinsic value? It's not because of their
functionality. Why does a diamond have I you know.
Stones, they're like totally it's like all a built-up market.
Exactly, exactly. All right, anyway, moving on. Okay, let's take
a Okay, now wait, I want to move I want to get
to the end of this topic. Okay. אמר רב דימי בר חנינא
Amar Rav Dimi bar Chanina הדר ביה רבא Hadar beh Rava מחלוקת
רבי שמעון ורבנן היא. machlokes Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbanan hi.
This statement of Rava that exempts you from these various things and
that isn't concerned about indirect loss of value is basically based on
a debate of Rabbi Shimon and the Rabbis. רבי שמעון דאמר דבר
הגורם לממון כממון דמי. Rabbi Shimon d'amar davar hagorem l'mamon k'mamon dami.
Everyone remembers this. Rabbi Shimon basically says that if you have a
if you steal from me a קרבן korban that because I don't
have it I'm going to have to replace it, so the loss
of that קרבן korban caused me a loss of money because I
have an obligation to bring a קרבן korban you took it from
me I have to replace it, so you have to pay me
back and you have to pay me כפל kefel because the fact
that its loss caused me money makes it like it's my קרבן
korban my property, okay, even though it really is הקדש. hekdesh. It
makes it like it's mine because its loss causes me the replacement
value. So Rabbi Shimon who says דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי davar
hagorem l'mamon k'mamon dami מחייב, mechayiv, you have to pay in all
these cases because basically you caused the person a loss of money.
So you basically the גמרא is seeing that that idea is sort
of like גרמא. Grama, You have to pay somebody for their loss.
ורבנן דאמרי דבר הגורם לממון לאו כממון דמי. v'Rabbanan d'amri davar hagorem
l'mamon lav k'mamon dami. The Rabbis who are not concerned because of
the causing a loss לא מחייב, lo mechayiv, you don't have to.
Now the גמרא is going to say they're not exactly the same.
מתקיף לה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. Maskif lah Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua. Rav Huna challenges. אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי שמעון דבר הגורם
לממון כממון דמי, Eima d'shamas lei l'Rabbi Shimon davar hagorem l'mamon k'mamon
dami, when did Rabbi Shimon say that if you cause a loss
it's treated like money? בדבר שעיקרו ממון, B'davar she'ikaro mamon,
something that started off as being of real money, meaning you had
a cow that was worth money, you sanctified it, and the real
question here is not did you destroy an object of value which
you did, the question is sort of like who owns it. Is
it considered to have, you know, to have value, is it considered
to be your cow, okay, so because it's going to cause you
a loss of money you're seen as the owner and that's seen
as the value. Okay, but that's very different than when you didn't
do an act of damage, okay, and the and the whole loss
was
indirect.
you stole חמץ Chametz before פסח Pesach and somebody burned it during
פסח Pesach or רש"י Rashi says on the 14th when everybody's supposed
to be burning their חמץ, Chametz, פטור. patur You don't have- I
stole חמץ Chametz here from David, okay. Jenna came and she burned
the חמץ. Chametz. Now I could say, "Jenna, you gotta pay me"
because I could have given that חמץ Chametz back to David and
been פטור patur from my obligation. But no, she burned it on
פסח, Pesach, everybody's supposed to be burning their or before פסח Pesach
everyone's supposed to be burning it. She didn't do anything wrong. שהכל
מצווין עליו לבערו. she-hakol metsuvin alav leva'aro. That's when everybody's supposed to
be burning it. ואחר פסח ve-achar Pesach now, let's say I stole
it, held it till after פסח. Pesach. Now it's worthless, it's חמץ
שעבר עליו הפסח. Chametz she-avar alav hapesach. But it's worth something to
me because I can return it to David and say הרי שלך
לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. That's our משנה. Mishnah. Since there's no physical
change in it, I say "Here's the חמץ Chametz back that I
stole." Even though it's worthless now, I am free now from my
obligation from having stolen it. So to everybody else it's worthless, to
me it's worth money because I can use it to get off
of my obligation. And in that case, okay, and Jenna came and
she burned it.
If you can return it, what's your obligation?
To pay him for the thousand dollars of חמץ Chametz that I
took on the ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. I stole it
בשעת גזילה, bish'at gezeilah, right.
Okay, so then Jenna came and then she destroyed this. So in
this case, מחלוקת רבי שמעון ורבנן. machloket Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabbanan.
That's the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן. Rabbanan.
דרבי שמעון אמר דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי, de-Rabbi Shimon amar davar
ha-gorem le-mamon ke-mamon dami, since its loss of this חמץ Chametz is
going to cause me a loss of money, חייב. chayav. You're חייב.
chayav. It's like it has value because to me it has value
and I'm considered the owner and therefore you have to pay me.
לרבנן דאמרי דבר הגורם לממון לאו כממון דמי, le-Rabbanan de-amrei davar ha-gorem
le-mamon lav ke-mamon dami, פטור patur because the רבנן Rabbanan who don't
give that weight that it's going to cause me loss, פטור patur
because it's worthless. Okay, that's true because we're dealing with something, a
real physical object that had initial value, that was actually destroyed, and
the only use of this idea of דבר הגורם לממון davar ha-gorem
le-mamon is just to say because its value to me defines what
its value is and I'm considered to be the owner and that
defines its value. But that's when it was an object that had
real intrinsic value that was a real act of
מזיק. mazik. Okay, בדבר שאין עיקרו ממון, bi-davar she'ein ikaro mamon, something
that intrinsically isn't an object of value like this case of the
שטר shtar for example, מי אמרינן? mi amrinan? Who said we would
say it? That's just a גרמא בניזקין grama be-nezikin case. So you
got דבר הגורם לממון davar ha-gorem le-mamon is when something's market value
is zero but subjective value is high. Okay, or it could also
be even when I'm not technically considered the owner, like the גמרא
has a case that I was a שומר, shomer, it became a
שור הנסקל shor haniskal and I'm not the owner, but because I
could return it to the owner, my subjective loss makes me like
the owner. So that's to give a dollar value to it and
to make me like the owner. That's דבר הגורם לממון. davar ha-gorem
le-mamon. But if something doesn't have any intrinsic value, it's a שטר,
shtar, it's only an abstract loss, it's an indirect causation, my coin
is at the bottom of the sea, okay, that's a case of
גרמא בניזקין. grama be-nezikin. That's not דבר הגורם לממון. davar ha-gorem le-mamon.
And that you cannot say would be חייב.
The coin at the bottom of the sea has intrinsic value.
But but you weren't מזיק it. You caused me indirect loss. That's
exactly the point. If the issue is not is not, "Oh, the
object doesn't have value, technically you're not the owner," the issue is
I didn't do an act of מזיק. I just caused you indirect
loss. That's not relevant for the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, so let's finish this point up. So
אמר מימר, amar Meimar, so now the גמרא is going to try
to fill the gap.
מאן דדן דיני דגרמי, man de-dan dinei de-garmi, ah, but the one,
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who we know does the laws of גרמי.
garmi. Now there's a big מחלוקת ראשונים machloket Rishonim what exactly גרמי
garmi is, is it a קנס, knas, is it a תקנה, takkanah,
but clearly for many it's coming to fill exactly this hole. It's
coming to say there's all these cases of גרמא Grama you could
technically get out of, the ones we shouldn't be getting out of
we're going to call גרמי. garmi. The רמב"ן Ramban wrote a whole
קונטרס דגרמי, kuntres de-garmi, like a big treatise on trying to figure
out what the parameters are, and it might not have clearly defined
parameters. But the bottom line is its function is to fill the
gap and to say that all these גרמא בניזקין grama be-nezikin you're
פטור from, the ones we decide you should be paying for we're
calling them גרמי garmi and you have to pay for
it. מאן דדן דיני דגרמי מגבי בדמי שטר מעליא man de-dan dinei
de-garmi magbi be-damei shtar ma'alya collects the full value of the שטר.
shtar. Now I don't know what that means. Does that mean the
face value of the שטר, shtar, the thousand dollars, because even a
שטר shtar that's worth a thousand dollar loan might not be worth
a thousand dollars. You don't know you're going to be able to
collect it or not. Maybe it means the- you know, what I
could sell it
for. ומאן דלא דן דיני דגרמי מגבי בדמי ניירא בעלמא, u-man de-lo
dan dinei de-garmi magbi be-damei niyara be-alma, you just get paid for
the piece of paper. And now the גמרא ends this story, הוה
עובדא, hava uvda, there was a case, דכפייה רפרם לרב אשי. de-kafye
Rafram le-Rav Ashi. Apparently רב אשי Rav Ashi just burned a שטר,
shtar, and רפרם Rafram made him
pay ואגבי ביה ככשורא לצלמא, ve-agbi beh ke-khashura le-tsalma, made him pay
like, you know, wood you would use in a constructor, like, you
know, the full value of it. Okay, so here you see a
case of גרמי garmi is coming to fill the gap. Before we
end I want to say רש"י Rashi is bothered, which is what
is רב אשי Rav Ashi doing burning people's שטרות? shtaros? Right. So
רש"י Rashi says- רש"י Rashi says he makes this up, but רש"י
Rashi says... רב אשי Rav Ashi did it when he was a
kid, and that’s how we can explain why he did it, and
there רפרם Rafram made him pay. So this leads to a great
discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim, if you damage something as a kid,
do you have to pay for it as an adult? Okay, because
why is רפרם Rafram making him pay if he did it as,
this is all because of רש״י said this. Okay, and maybe
you’re חייב בדיני שמים chayav bdinei shamayim ופטור בדיני אדם, upattur bdinei
adam, maybe there’s some moral obligation if you did it as a
kid? So that gets read into this רש״י’s read here because he
doesn’t want רב אשי Rav Ashi to be burning people’s שטרות. Shtaros.
Okay, but the bigger point here is that גרמי Garmi becomes a
category where there’s a major debate ראשונים Rishonim but its function is
to close this gap for when גרמא, the laws of גרמא would
mean that you would be exempt.